[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
now how much people after Michaelson
Morley really there were all kinds of
explanations of Michaelson moley
experiment ether drift that The Ether
was being swept along with the Earth and
so
forth or Loren contraction yeah I mean
Lawrence contraction of course was
correct but uh the way lorence thought
about it is things moving relative to
The Ether somehow got squeezed by The
Ether well I suppose you could always
describe it that way but it was a it
wasn't the the right way that Einstein
thought about it in the end so they had
these mechanistic descriptions they had
these mechanis mechanistic attempts at
explanations which were not the real
far-reaching principle that the that
Einstein came to so I don't know how
much the Michaelson moley experiment
really shook the foundations but it
certainly was a signal that uh that
there was something going on that was
different than what they expected so
Michaelson Morley and you you does
everybody know what the proper what the
problem with the radiation was the
problem with black body
radiation ultraviolet catastroph the
ultraviolet catastrophe well if not I'll
explain it right now
um it was a conflict it was a conflict
between two sets of principles one
principle was the wave theory of light
and the wave theory of light said that
light could come light electromagnetic
radiation could come in any wavelength
whatever each wavelength behaved like a
harmonic oscillator the mathematics of a
wave of a given wavelength is just the
mathematics of an
oscillation
so and this was understood long before
the quantum mechanics of oscillations
was understood in the late uh 19th
century that the mechanics of light the
mechanics of uh not just light any kind
of waves that each wave was basically a
harmonic oscillator each wavelength of
wave that was number
one uh the other thing that it was in
conflict with with was the principle of
statistical mechanics according to the
principles of statistical mechanics
there's a something called the equip
partition of
energy that if you have a collection of
harmonic oscillators and it doesn't
matter what the frequency of the
oscillators are there many many
different oscillators with different
frequencies when they come into thermal
equilibrium each one has the same amount
of energy basically it said that the
energy of an oscillation
is equal to boltzman's constant times
the temperature quite independently of
what the uh of what the frequency of the
oscillator is all right so now you have
light in a cavity or electromagnetic
radiation in a cavity and in that cavity
you can have waves bouncing back and
forth you can't have waves which of
course are longer than the size of the
cavity they won't fit into the cavity
but you can have waves of arbitrary wave
wavelength that will fit into the cavity
very small
wavelengths wavelengths like that that
just barely fit into the cavity and
every single wavelength corresponds to a
harmonic oscillator according to the
principles of of statistical mechanics
according to the principles of boltzman
and Maxwell and and Gibbs and the other
people who invented statistical
mechanics every one of these
oscillations should have exactly the
same amount of energy
well that just means an infinite amount
of energy because there's an infinite
number of different kinds of waves that
can be supported inside the cavity well
that's a disaster if you bring the
cavity to thermal equilibrium and it has
an infinite number of different kinds of
oscillations each with the same energy
then there's an infinite amount of
energy in the
cavity and it would simply melt the
cavity or vaporize the cavity or destroy
the cavity in one way or another
the result is something was deeply wrong
now how wrong people didn't really know
they thought maybe there was something
wrong with the way the uh the atoms
emitted radiation for some reason they
didn't emit very high frequency
radiation nobody really
knew um plank did not recognize plank
was not the one who recogn he did write
down e equal H
new no he wrote down E equals
n * H new he did say that energy comes
in discrete
multiples of a certain constant times
the frequency of oscillators and it
comes in multiples of that he did write
that down but he was not thinking about
the radiation in the
cavity his theory was that the
oscillators in the walls the walls of
the cavity the things which emitted the
radiation the those things had
frequencies which were integer multiples
of H new okay that was his theory and
therefore could only emit radiation of
um of integer multiples of eal H new he
didn't have a correct theory of what was
going on he wrote this equation down but
the equation didn't apply to uh to the
radiation in the O in the in the cavity
it applied to the things in the walls
according to plunk he managed to fit the
curves of black body radiation
correctly uh he managed to reproduce the
spectrum of black body radiation but by
arguments which really didn't make sense
the main thing in the argument is that
there was a
parameter uh H in the
problem the way we understand it now is
to say you simply can't have in a an
each one of these oscillations you can't
have less than one
Quantum okay if each Quantum if each
oscillator has the same
energy and you take oscillators which
have very very high
frequency then they will have to have
less than one
Quantum in other words if e if E equals
KT and KT is a certain number
temperature boltzman's constant is just
a numerical constant whatever the
temperature
is then there will be frequencies which
are so large that this energy is less
than one
Quantum one Quantum of energy according
to classical physics no problem you can
have a oscillator with any amount of
energy according to Quantum Mechanics
you cannot have less than one Quantum of
worth of energy less than one Quantum
means no Quant and so Einstein idea was
that the waves inside the cavity were
quantized and all those waves which had
frequencies so large or wavelength so
small that H new exceeded KT they just
wouldn't be there that was Einstein's
idea they wouldn't be there because you
couldn't have less than one Photon per
uh uh for each
oscillator so now at first of course
people did not believe
Einstein that light was composed of
particles that it was composed of
discrete
quanta for
about 20 years less a little bit less
than 20 years for about 18 years people
Einstein was very famous they all agreed
he had done something wonderful when he
had said that the radiation inside the
cavity had E equals h no but yet they
didn't believe it they thought there was
going to be some way to wiggle out and
somehow the wave theory of life would
wind up being correct they didn't
believe it they didn't believe it until
experiments were done where
light shines off atoms gives the atom a
kick and radiation goes off in other
directions this the compant effect the
comptant effect of scattering of Light
by charged particles and it was
discovered that the energies and angles
exactly conformed to what you would
expect from the scattering of particles
particles come in particles go out and
if you use energy and momentum
conservation then you can predict
various things about the Angles and
energy that the radiation goes off in
those things did not follow just from
wave theory they follow from wave theory
supplemented uh with the idea that the
radiation comes in discrete packets and
when those experiments were done it
basically took 18 years for people to
buy into the theory of photons and
within weeks literally within weeks or
maybe it was months I'm not sure
everybody agreed light is made out of
photons so it was one of these critical
things that happens all of a sudden and
you wonder why it took so long but uh
but a certain particular experiment
sharply uh sharply separated the time
when people believed in photons until
they didn't by that time of course
everybody knew that the foundations of
classical mechanics were wrong when it
came to atoms but they didn't want to
believe that the wave theory of light
was wrong of course the wave theory of
light was not wrong it was just sort of
incomplete didn't the photoelectric
effect show that there are photons way
yeah you would think that the
photoelectric effect would have been
enough but psychologically it was not
enough right
exactly yeah I've got a candidate date
of
1915 when uh when Bo explained the
hydrogen atom 193 13 yeah
uh uh using Plank's constant yeah yeah
yeah when he when he reproduced the
ridberg constant from plant when he
reproduced the r ridberg constant the
levels of uh yeah that was certainly a
very critical time but that was not
enough for them to buy into the photon
Theory
so uh the photon theory of light they
didn't buy into yet they did recognize
that something radically different uh
was governing the motion of atoms and
electrons in atoms than classical
mechanics and that that's absolutely
right I mean uh uh
B's explanation of atomic levels was a
sharp uh a sharp transition so there
were several sharp transitions but the
the whole thing stretched itself out
over about 20 years from 19 well 25
years from
1900 Plank's discovery of the plun
constant to basically
1926 27 something like that with uh well
26 which was Schrodinger Heisenberg and
a little bit later durak putting the
elements together it was Einstein it was
Einstein who
understood most clearly and most said it
most forcefully very early I'm not sure
exactly what year uh very early that
whatever's going on because of this new
Quantum structure one had to one had to
suppose that nature was fundamentally
not
deterministic he was the one who said
that the emission of radiation he
realized was a spontaneous he he spoke
about spontaneous emission of photons
from atoms and from other things and he
understood that it was not deterministic
that it was essentially uh probabilistic
and it was he who first said nature is
not the he he who first said God rolls
Dice and
uh and uh it was
uh not bore not uh not uh uh not bore
not born anybody else who was Einstein
who said that first and
uh I think it's kind of interesting
though that uh that bore and and the
people who were working with the Adam
were still working with with uh
essentially
part particles and specific orbits and
things like that yes yes and they were
trying to it to to to get theum
effects that's right so it's not
completely clear that they recognize the
magnitude of their
problem when when Heber yeah finally
decided something something's wrong with
the whole thing
junk yeah but as I said um Einstein had
already said the world is not determined
istic and you can never ever know enough
to uh to be able to predict uh uh the
emission of the time of emission of a
photon there's nothing you can do to
measure that you can measure enough to
know when an atom is going to Decay he
also talked about radioactivity the same
way he said there's nothing you can do
no measurement that you can make in the
atom uh he he sensed that he could tell
from what was going on that
uh
that physics was fundamentally limited
to probabilistic uh uh explanations of
things I'm just wondering if since every
observation of a photon involves an
electron or some charged particle some
charge isn't it enough that one of those
particles is quantized um it's enough to
that one of them is quantized to prove
that the other
is
uh you really can't you really can't
couple together classical things to
quantum mechanical things it doesn't
make sense you run into you run into
contradictions uh trying to keep part of
a part of a theory classical and the
rest quantum mechanical it really does
run itself into the ground uh pretty
quickly so it's enough to know that one
is quantum mechanical to know that the
other has to be quantum
mechanical um but
uh yeah yeah so so why did Einstein
never really accept the theory I mean
he's never really satisfied with quanum
mechanics even though what you just said
I he he was one of the first said well I
I don't really
know um I don't really know if I had to
guess I would guess he was very very
uncomfortable with the idea of a
probabilistic
theory what does probability mean you
flip a coin a thousand times what ises
does it tell you about nature that the
probability is 50% heads 50% Tails does
it tell you anything about nature does
does it tell you that uh that it will
turn up heads 500 times no it doesn't
tell you that does it tell you 500 times
within the margin of error the margin of
error being what square of
1,30 no it doesn't tell you that does it
tell you that you cannot flip a thousand
heads no it doesn't tell you that what
does it tell you it tells you that it's
improbable to flip uh a thousand heads
well probability is being defined in
terms of probability what ultimately
does it say about nature that uh that if
you flip a coin a thousand times that
the probability is a heads that it will
turn up uh the probability is 50% that
it'll turn up
heads I think the only thing I can think
of that makes sense is to say you'd be
very very surprised if you're outside
the
[Music]
tonight I think if we can get to it we
will understand the connection with
classical mechanics why momentum in
quantum mechanics which uh is one thing
is related to momentum In classical
mechanics which is another
thing uh what energy why
energy why the hamiltonian of quantum
mechanics is called Energy and so forth
and of course the answer is because in
contexts where things are heavy enough
to behave according to approximate
classical mechanics these quantities
that have been defined in quantum
mechanics behave approximately like the
corresponding Quant quantities In
classical mechanics all right but always
keep in mind quantum mechanics is more
fundamental you don't derive quantum
mechanics from classical mechanics you
derive the other way so that's what
we're going to do tonight but let's come
back to the Schrodinger equation let me
remind you what it is it says it's the
equ which tells you how the state Vector
changes with time it contains Plank's
constant H
bar and it says that the rate of change
of the state
Vector with respect to
time is equal to an operator a Herm
Mission observable operator that's
called
H when I remember to do so I put a
little hat on top of it to indicate that
it's an operator acting on
S that's called the general we we should
call it the general Schrodinger equation
of course it's not the exact thing that
Schrodinger wrote
down all right we'll supplement this I
want to make a list of some of the
equations that we
need another equation is that momentum
this says that energy is related to time
derivatives with a factor of I bar a
similar equation
similar looking equation is that
momentum I don't need to momentum is an
operator its whole purpose in life is to
act on a state Vector I won't bother
writing uh well maybe I will write n
let's not write a state Vector for it
let's just write P that that's equal to
minus i h d by
DX in other words the the time
derivative of the wave
function is obtained by the hamiltonian
acting on the wave function the space
derivative of the wave function is
related to the momentum Operator by the
same factor
iar the minus sign in there the fact
that there's a minus sign here and no
minus sign here is something of a
convention uh it just historically
evolved that way that there's a minus
sign here here and no minus sign here we
could change
conventions and put a minus sign there
too we won't because after all but these
are
venerable uh conventions so we'll stick
with
them all right now last but not least
we're thinking about a particle moving
along a
line it has a hamiltonian and here's
where we use classical physics to make a
guess not a derivation but a
guess pure guess that the hamiltonian of
classical physics now so far we don't
know any particular relationship between
this hamiltonian and the classical
physics
hamiltonian but that's equal to a free
particle to p^2 over 2
m the fact that it's proportional to p^2
and not P let's start with that P is a
vector which for a particle moving along
a line means that it has either a
forward sense or a backward sense
momentum can go this way or it can go
this way all right we wouldn't want the
energy to depend on whether the momentum
is in that direction or in that
direction we expect that the energy of a
particle moving to the left with a
certain momentum is the same as the
energy of a particle moving to the right
with the same
momentum and so it makes a lot of sense
to say that it's proportional to p^ squ
and not P if P was here by
itself uh then the energy would be
opposite for positive momentum and
negative
momentum the fact that there's a 2N here
well that's essentially the definition
of mass if you like again you could call
it something else you don't need to call
it m but the fact is that energy energy
is proportional to p^2 over 2m fairly
general fact about ordinary
non-relativistic
particles so we make the guess we try it
out and see what we learn from it to
suppose that the hamiltonian of quantum
mechanics is also p^2 over
2m but now it's in the sense of
operators the operator H is the
operator p^ squar over 2
m and as I said keep in mind the real
derivation goes from this Blackboard to
this black board and we're going to do
that derivation
tonight
uh so let's see what that means what is
the meaning of this equation and how
does it connect together with the other
equations above it the only other thing
you need to know is what it means I
wrote down what p is what does p^ squ
mean p^ squ simply means you act twice
with the same operator you'll act with
the operator on a way on a state vector
and then you operate with it again once
followed by the second time all right so
this is enough for us to now write down
the Schrodinger equation for a free
particle instead of
writing the K Vector S I will just
remember that wave function s of X form
a vector
space the wave function is in general
not just a function of
position it is a function of position
it's squar tells you the probability for
finding the particle at different
locations but of course it's also
implicitly a function of
time it changes with time its dependence
on time is logically of a different kind
than its dependence on Space the state
Vector is s of X but the state Vector
changes with time okay so that's the way
to think about it now we wouldn't speak
for example about SAR s being the
probability for different
times that doesn't make any sense what's
the probability that the time is such
and such well that doesn't make any
sense but it does make sense to say
what's the probability that the particle
is located at a particular position at a
certain time so the dependence on x and
t are quite logically quite different X
is an observable of course when I look
at my clock I also observe the time but
what I'm really doing is observing the
position of the hands on the clock those
are
positions okay so let's write down the
shinger equation now all we have to do
is substitute into the top
equation and we get what do we get we
get I
let's let's uh pull
down we get I
HR DC of x and t by DT that's the left
hand
side the right hand
side we use H is equal to P ^2 over 2m
so first of all is a 1 over 2
m and then PX twice p is minus i h d by
DX so we get minus I HR d by
DX but we write it twice Min - i h Bar D
by
DX acting on S of x and t
all right so what does this mean the
first D first of all we can take out the
factor of minus I bar squared - I * - I
is
-1 so first of all let's get rid of the
I's that gives us our overall minus sign
there's an har bar squared so let's take
out the H bar
squared and we have d by DX mult
multiplying the d d by DX * s d DX * s
just means it means nothing but
derivative of s with respect to
X differentiating it again just gives us
the second derivative so this whole
thing becomes nothing but the second
derivative with respect to
X of s of
X and that's our shrodinger
equation that's the shinger equation for
a free
particle it's the actual equation that
schinger actually wrote
down we could get into why he wrote this
down but let's not uh let's just pursue
it and work at it from the other end and
we'll eventually see why he wrote it
down okay now let's look for Solutions
of this equation let's look for
Solutions which have the character of
being plain waves let's look like for
wavelike Sol Solutions in other words
let's look for Solutions whose x
dependence is of the
form e to the
i p h
x let's look for Solutions of that
type um y p over H bar well I can I can
just describe them that way p uh that uh
let's say
y p over H bar well if I
differentiate just just look for
Solutions of that
form H you want Omega there maybe no I
don't want Omega there Omega multiplies
time okay so let's put in Omega Omega
has to do with time dependence let's put
in a factor e to the
I Omega
t other words let's assume that the wave
function oscillates with time and
oscillates with space the justification
for this will be that do that they do
exist Solutions like this right these
Solutions if we find them will at any
instant of time the igen vectors of the
momentum operator remember igen vectors
of the momentum operator have the
form as wave
functions e to the i px/ a H
bar those are igen vectors of the
momentum operator they're the things
which minus i d by
DX uh act on to give an i they're igon
vectors they're igen vectors of uh of
the momentum operator all right the time
dependence here well this tells us that
wave functions have time dependence and
I'm guessing I'm guessing now that they
oscillate with time that's an
oscillation typical oscillation let's
plug this into the Schrodinger equation
and see if we can find out what Omega is
Omega is the unknown of course there may
be no such solution like this we may
find that it U that you know we uh we
run the bus into the
ditch that we can't find Solutions like
this but of course if we couldn't I
wouldn't have written it
down okay what happens if we take s of X
and differentiate it with respect to
time every time we differentiate with
respect to time we pull down a factor of
I
Omega so the left hand side is just
going to be give us an i
Omega time
I times s itself here's s all right when
I differentiate with respect to time
it'll give me back the same thing except
with an i Omega in front of it so that's
just s of
x and
t i Omega * I that's just
minus H
Omega now let's look on the right hand
side on the right hand side every time I
differentiate with respect to X it pulls
down i p over HR it gives me a factor of
i p over H bar
so let's write it all down is equal to
minus H bar
s over 2
m incidentally I could have canceled out
a factor of H bar from here so that only
so it doesn't appear here and only
appears once here we'll do it we'll do
it in this form now what is the second
derivative of s the second derivative of
s just contains this Factor squared i p
over h s so that gives me i^
2 is
-1 that turns this minus sign into a
plus sign it gives me p^
2 over H bar
s and then just s
again all right so now let's clean it up
a little bit h squ H bar squ that
cancels cancel out the H
bars and we get p ^2 / 2
m *
s the left hand side minus Omega * H bar
Time s the right hand side p^2 over 2 m
Time s cancel out the size and what do
we find we find that the frequency minus
Omega must
equal
p² over 2
m uh yes divided 2 MH thank
you now what we're doing from a
mathematical point of view is actually
finding the igen
vectors one for one way of saying it is
find we're finding the igen values of
the hamiltonian
Omega when the H okay let's uh let's
we'll come back to it we'll come back to
the igen values of the hamiltonian
that's what Omega basically is an igen
value of the
hamiltonian but we find that the omegas
have to be equal to minus P ^2 over 2 MH
Bar let's now use that to
rewrite the wave function the wave
function that we found now has the form
of x and
t and of course this is only one of many
solutions uh is of the form e to the i p
over
HR
xus
I p^ 2/ 2 m HR
T so it oscillates with X and it
oscillates with t the X oscillation is
governed by the momentum itself
itself and the T oscillation is governed
by the momentum if we forget the H bars
in a little while I'll probably set H
bar equal to one notice how H bar comes
into these formulas it always comes
comes in in the form of a coordinate now
a coordinate I can either mean X or t
think of both x's and T's as being
coordinates it always comes in in the
form X over H or t over h
once you know that you can set har to
one and recover it later by sticking it
back into the
equations X over har is the only way in
which plunk constant enters into this
wave function and T of har bar so every
time you see X and every time you see T
put an H bar in the denominator and that
will recover for you the fact is a
plunks
constant all right so here was the this
is the simplest solution
of the Schrodinger equation for a free
particle it corresponds to a particle of
momentum p and energy p^2 over 2
m notice there is another wave function
which corresponds to exactly the same
energy what is
it if this is a particle moving to the
right it corresponds to a momentum P
which is positive then there's another
one if we fix P fix p p is some positive
number for example the energy is p squar
over 2 m there are two states two
configurations with the same energy one
has P going that way the other has P
going that way so there's another wave
function we could have written down I'll
write it down side by side with this
which would have had the form e to Theus
i p over
HX
but the time dependence is exactly the
same why is that that's because this
only depends on p^
S all right so if I change the sign of P
it doesn't change the sign of p^2 and
it's minus i p ^2 / 2 m HR T these are
two wave functions which both correspond
to the same energy but opposite going
momentum you can add them together with
arbitrary
coefficients they will no longer be igen
vectors of the momentum because you're
mixing together two momenta but they
will have the same
energy so if you add wave functions like
this the energies the energy of the wave
of the combined wave function is still
p^2 over 2 m 2 m not n
m but you're mixing two
momenta depending on the the
coefficients that you would put these
two together with let's put them
together with some
coefficients let's call this one alpha
and let's call this one
beta all right what's the probability
that the particle is moving to the
right Alpha star
alpha alpha star Alpha is the
coefficient of the igen vector with
Right Moving momentum and the
probability that it's moving to the left
is beta star beta what's the probability
that it has energy p^ s over to
m one right
one all right so this is a simple
example what constitutes the special
relation I don't know
special
relationship like knocked me off
balance all right now what's the general
solution these this is a special
solution of the shringer equation
corresponding or it's a family of
special Solutions with an alpha and a
beta but they they all correspond to the
same energy what is the general solution
of the schinger equation the general
solution is sums or
integrals of wave functions like this we
can take wave functions of the form e to
the I p/ HR x - i p ^ 2 / 2 m h
t and now we can add them or better yet
with added them there but now we can
better yet integrate them
DP and just for reasons of convention I
put in the standard square root of 2 pi
here but you don't need to times an
amplitude s of P or S twidle of
P now in this expression here I don't
have to include a left moving and a
Right Moving momentum since I'm
integrating over P let's say from minus
infinity to Infinity there are
contributions in here where p is
positive and contributions where p is
negative so this wave
function which is a sum which is a
superposition a Quantum
superposition of states with different
momentum P very much like any Quantum
superposition it's a Quantum
superposition of states with different
momenta and also in general different
Energies it's true the left moving and
the right moving with the same value of
P have the same energy but in general
when I integrate up lots of different
momenta I have States in there of very
different energy so this is a Quantum
superposition that is not only a
superposition of different momenta but
also different
energies what's the probability for
example that this particle has momentum
P now when I say it has momentum P I
really mean the momentum density as a
function of P
because momentum is a continuous
variable we describe it by a momentum
density the probability that the
momentum is between p and p plus
DP but what's the probability
density for the momentum to be P well
that's just s star s twiddle of P Time s
twiddle star of P question yes uh I
thought the the dummy variable of
integration is p and oh okay yes yes the
dummy variable of integration is p good
thank you and so what is
the oh this is in the integral oh that's
in the integral that's in the integral
absolutely okay that's in the integral
what's the parameters of the the
parameters of what of
the the
parameters what's
fixed what is fixed x and
t I guess nothing is fixed nothing's
fixed yeah and and M yeah oh yeah sure
sure uh H bar is fixed m is fixed I is
fixed e is fixed Infinity is fixed Pi is
fixed two is
fixed
right but other than
that other than almost everything on the
board nothing is fix
we're integrating over P which means
we're suming up waves of different
wavelength we're summing up waves of
different wavelength some moving to the
right some moving to the left and we're
summing them up with an amplitude s of P
each wave has a Time dependence so we're
summing up these things each one is
oscillating the different one they're
oscillating with different
frequencies it's a mess the whole thing
is doing very very complicated things
but it can all be represented as a
superposition of different momentum igen
States all right now I come back to my
question what is the probability density
what's the probability density that the
particle has momentum let's say Q let's
not call it P since p is an integration
variable
probability density P of q that of
course is nothing but this amplitude
squared again it's the same sort of
thing we're adding up wave functions
with different uh
coefficients so this probability is s
Twi star of q s of
Q I've just picked a particular value of
momentum I didn't want to call it P
because in this formula p is an
integration
variable uh did I miss a twiddle thank
you
good all right it's a function of
momentum fun position no it's not a
function of position oh I'm sorry we
should uh you're thinking of ping Q's in
the sense of positions and momenta no uh
p q here is a
momentum yeah we could just call it P
prime or something yeah maybe I should
do that I no I don't have to I've
already established a notation the
position is
X and p's and q's both mean momenta here
but it's a it's it's a fair
point um if I use x for position then I
won't use Q for position good thank you
all right so this is the probability
that the particle has momentum Q what's
the probability that the energy is
e what's the probability that the energy
is e well the probability that the
energy is e you get two contributions
with the same energy you first WR write
e = p ^2 / 2
m that tells you what P to look for if I
want the probability that the particle
has energy E I look for those pieces of
the wave function where the momentum
satisfies p^2 over 2 m = e in other
words I look for p ^2 =
2me how many p² how many PS are there
such that p^2 is equal to 2 me two
namely
the two possible square
roots uh the two possible square roots
can this be seen no it can't but uh but
believe me there's a plus or minus sign
here plus or minus square root of 2me is
equal to P so what I do is I look in
this wave function or in this General
wave function here for the
contributions which have a given energy
there will be two of them
and the probability let's call these p+
minus p+ minus is plus or minus I'm
going to rewrite it I'm going to rewrite
it so everybody can see it P plus or
minus equals plus or minus now I forgot
what it
was square root of 2 m
right I think that's it yeah so what I
do is I go to for the two wave functions
in here which have this value of energy
right and I take the total probability
for that value of energy what's it going
to be it's going to be that probability
let's say probability for a given energy
is going to be S
twidle of
p+
star s twiddle of
p+ that's the probability that the
momentum is
p+ plus the
probability that the momentum is p
minus where p+ and P minus are just
opposite values of the momentum one
going one way one going the other way
all right so that's that's the uh the
shringer equation for a free
particle
H probably but I think by now I may have
uh where um yeah let no no not in
there not no no no
no no the energy in terms of the
momentum does not have an H
bar energy in terms of momentum is just
the same as in classical
physics so have we found General
solution
yeah that's the general solution of
the yep that's it and S of course can be
complex so it's parameterized by a
complex function of p and that's it
that's all of the solutions there are no
well I take that back there are other
Solutions but the other Solutions have
the property that they either blow up or
do something terrible in Infinity they
they uh they are they simply blow up at
Infinity these are all of the solutions
that don't blow up at
Infinity in other words which don't have
all of their probability way out at
Infinity this is all of them yeah all
the relevant Solutions does that depend
on the Assumption you made at the very
beginning that you can that they're
separable that you separate the the e to
the I Omega T and IX
h supposing they weren't separable would
that still be the general
solution if they weren't separable this
wouldn't be the equation and if this
weren't the equation this wouldn't be
the
solution let's talk about the case where
they're not
separable the case where they're not
separable separable just means the way
function factors no it's always
separable in the sense that uh that
there's a function of X which may not be
a simple e to the IX times an
oscillation in uh in t we'll prove that
we'll prove that I hope we'll prove that
I hope we have time to prove it is there
pH arbitrary phase yeah you can you can
put an AR you can put an arbitrary
coefficient here complex or
real yeah it will still any kind and in
fact these are the arbitrary Coe icient
so this could contain a
phase
okay dep on and the yeah the phase yeah
the S of P can contain a phase which
depends on P absolutely if it didn't
depend on P it wouldn't be very
interesting a phase that depends on P is
interesting in other words it affects
the uh uh the
probabilities
okay let's uh we want to come to a
more let's
see yeah just a second let me just see
my
notes
yeah s
twid s twiddle is the Foria transform of
s of X of s of X at time at Time Zero
supposing you go to Time Zero if we go
to time Z this this is a good question
let's let's uh pursue
it let's go to time tal 0 at time t
equal 0 this wave function is just minus
infinity to Infinity integral DP over
square root of 2 pi e to the I PX s ttle
of
P that's equal to S of X at time equal Z
let's just call it s of x this is the
definition of the Foria transform of s
of
x if we happen to have known here might
be the way we might set up a problem
supposing we knew that at time tals 0
the wave function of the particle was s
of X I don't know how we know we know
that the wave function is s of X at time
T equals 0 and we want to find it at a
later time what do we do well the first
thing we do is we find the fora
transform side twiddle of P let me
remind you how you do
that let's see let's put it up
here side twidle of
p is equal to the integral from minus
infinity to Infinity now not integral DP
but integral
d x integral
DX
e to Theus I
PX over < TK of 2 piun Time s of X so if
somebody tells us what s of X is at a
certain instant of time let's say at
time T equals z we can reconstruct what
s of p is remember now the reciprocal
relationship between for a transform of
X and Foria transform of P Foria
transforms are reciprocally related in
such a way that if s of X is an integral
e to the ipx sdle of P then s twidle of
p is integral same kind of integral
except over x with a minus sign up here
this is the reciprocal relationship
between uh wave between functions and
their fora
transforms right so your first find S
twiddle of P once you found s twiddle of
P you stick it into this formula
which is basically the same formula
except that it now has time
dependence and other words and this
becomes s of x and t this becomes s of x
and
t so you start out at time T equals 0
with some knowledge of the wave
function you compute the Foria transform
that tells you side to of P you then
stick it in to this time dependent
formula here the only time dependence is
that for each wave there's an e to the
i^2 over 2 m * T and that gives you the
full time dependence of the wave
function now the wave function will
evolve in a complicated way the
different waves that are in it are
oscillating with different time
dependencies so for example the shape of
the wave function will not be preserved
D if we start out with some general wave
function like that and we start evolving
it the different fora components
oscillate with different periods the
result is the whole thing is going to
move in a complicated pattern which is
not going to preserve a
shape but nevertheless that's the
evolution of the uh of
the of the wave function once you know
this you can then ask what's the
probability at a later time that the
particle is located in some particular
place so the kind of problem we might
solve is by hook or crook somebody tells
us what the uh what the initial wave
function is and what we want to find out
is not at that instant of
time what the probability for its
location is that's easy that's just s
star that's a sar of x s of X but we
want to find out what the probability
will be at a later time after all this
complicated uh MO is taking place what's
the probability to find the particle at
a particular place we go through this
operation we find S twiddle of P we plug
it into here that gives us s of x and t
we can put this on a computer calculate
s of x and t and then SAR of x and t * s
of x and t is the new probability at a
later time uh for locating the particle
in different places that's the logic
that's the logic that's the way quantum
mechanics
works
okay any other questions yes so so you
can also derive side twiddle of pnt also
involve the side twid side twiddle of
p&t is really just this
combination you see if I called all of
this everything here e let's put an e to
the minus I and group this
together all right then we see that we
can combine side totle of p with this
Factor here and this just becomes the
time dependent Foria transform of s of x
and t does that answer your question yes
good right so another way to say it is
that the Foria transform evolves with
time and it evolves with this phase
Factor
here but as I said the important thing
is this time dependence of the Foria
transform translates in General into a
rather complicated uh variation of the
wave function with time but you can
always find it in this way yeah if the
wave doesn't preserve its shape with
time that that's a dispersive wave and
it means the different components
propagate at different speed
absolutely right that this is
true
right
um
right the difference components do
propagate with different speed for
sure it's not surprising since the
different components correspond to
different
momenta in fact there are several
different kinds of speeds group velocity
phase velocity and so forth but uh
um I won't do that now group velocity
and phase velocity in uh yeah
okay remind me to tell you something
about the schedule because uh for this
class because
I will be gone for some period And I
don't want you to show up here when I
won't be
here remind you
when uh when I'm off the
air
okay now the next thing we want to do is
we want to study the evolution of the
expectation values first of all we want
to study a more complicated kind of
Schrodinger equation in which the
particle is subjected to
forces in which the particle is moving
in the presence of a potential of a
potential function that's one thing
we're going to want to do and work out
the Schrodinger equation but the other
thing we're going to want to do is once
we've done that we want to see how wave
packets move a wave packet is simply a
concentrated uh wave of some sort which
moves along with some sort of coherent
motion
the center of w the center of the wave
packet or the average position of the
wave packet moves in some way and it had
better be that at least in the
appropriate circumstances that the
motion of the wave packet looks pretty
much like the corresponding motion of a
classical uh system of a classical
particle we're going to want to work
that out we'll do that
tonight uh but before we study the more
complicated schinger equation I want to
remind you how you calculate the time
evolution of expectation values cuz
that's what we're going to do we're
going to do it for the Stringer
equation uh so two
steps question yeah just a quick
question so that that equation there for
S of X so that could be for Photon
right well photons are not
non-relativistic particles this is
really the theory of non-relativistic
particles so you wouldn't apply this in
this form to a photon
photons uh simply don't have energies
which are p^ s over 2 m in fact they
don't have any
M so you wouldn't apply it in quite this
form to a
photon is that the question yeah yeah
you would have
to
uh the rule is that this is an
appropriate description for particles
moving much much slower than the speed
of light
okay um question is whether I should
well I'm trying to yeah
okay let's put a little variety into
this let's back off the particle on a
line and remind ourselves how we compute
the time dependence of expectation
values then we'll come back to a more
complicated version of a particle moving
on a
line let's
take
some
observable Ah that's a surprise red
let's take a observable let's call it
K and let's take its average value its
expectation
value there's its expectation
value right and let's study its time
dependence this is the closest thing to
the corresponding classical
evolution of that
observable right it's expectation
value to calculate and we're imagining
some fixed observable the observable
itself is not changing with time it
could be position it could be momentum
it could be spin could be polarization
but we're not changing it with time what
is changing with time is the state
vectors so we use the rule for
differentiating products K is not time
dependent but the two sides here are and
let's write this just in the form bra
Vector time derivative the dot indicates
time derivative
k
s plus s k Time s
dot I'm going over stuff which we did
last
time now we use the Schrodinger equation
let's use the Schrodinger equation over
here for side dot side dot is either
plus or minus
i h i I am now going to set H bar equal
to
1 H bar equal to one because it'll drive
me crazy to keep track of it in these
equations H bar is equal to one does
anybody remember whether the side dot is
plus I * H SI or minus I * H SI I
don't minus
I side dot is is the same thing as s
k and now s dot is I forgot what I just
said did I say minus or
plus
h minus I so Min - I this one is minus I
I hope I'm right * H *
s notice we have K over here and H over
here how about this one over here this
one over here we have to apply the time
Evolution to the bra Vector that
involves a complex
conjugation the minus I will become a
plus I this becomes
i
s
h
k
s we have two different terms one of
them has HK the other one has KH the
result is
I times the expectation value of the
commutator of H with
K remember what the commutator is it's
HK minus
KH I won't bother putting in the size
here I just indicate the expectation
value of the commutator of H and K
that's the rule in fact let's just write
this as the time derivative
of the expectation value of K for any
state it doesn't matter what state we
choose that is the way the expectation
value will evolve now of course both
sides will depend on what state we're
talking
about the relationship between the two
is always the same but the actual
magnitude of each of these sides depends
on what state we're talking about all
right this is the rule that we're going
to use to try to figure out how evolve
in the shinger how the motion of a wave
packet evolves in
time for example we could apply this to
the position to X to X itself to the
position operator and find out how the
POS how the average position of a
particle changes with time we could
apply it to the momentum and find out
how the average momentum of a particle
changes with time so let's put this
upstairs and keep it uh for future
reference while we do a couple of other
simple
things
evidently we're going to have to compute
commutators commutators are the things
that we're going to have to compute to
see how things evolve with time so let's
study a little bit about commutators in
quantum
mechanics just a few simple
things oh incidentally let's compare
this with another
equation the corresponding classical
equation is that the time
derivative of an observable we won't put
brackets around it now because now it
really means the time derivative of some
classical quantity anybody remember what
it's given
by by the Plus
bracket the pone
bracket I can't remember if it's K with
H or H with
K I always have trouble with these signs
h k with h are you sure are you
absolutely sure
yeah okay I'll trust
you so how come it's
reversed well first of all there's an i
in there among other things I doubt that
it is reversed um let me just uh find my
own
[Applause]
notes I have H with K in my
notes we can find out fast
enough everybody send you an email H
everybody will send you an email that's
true but I'm going to write H with K
time had it the other way last time I
had it the other way around K with h
well it's one way or the
other
uh okay let's figure it
out okay let's figure it
out we have some function let's call it
K since we've already called it
k k of X and P for example
the time derivative of K of X and P is
equal to the derivative of K with
respect to x times the derivative of x
just the xdt let's call it x
dot plus the derivative of K with
respect to
P time P dot I I don't like this red pen
but I'm but I've sort of run out of
black pins no I haven't here's another
one
let's hope it's got something in it all
right this is true now do you remember
Hamilton's equations Hamilton's
equations say that x dot is the
hdp so this is the
HTP and that's correct really is the HTP
not minus the
hdp P dot is
minus
dhdx this is is
correct now what is this this is the
Pome bracket of K with h you were right
Michael I
think what did you say you did that in
your head while I was
oh K with h is right okay so you can
always go back to the uh basic principle
and figure out what's going on that's
correct uh is it possible that we made a
mistake in the quantum mechanics I I
can't tell I'm not sure sign of the i h
could be the sign of the IH that CH
yeah it could be and maybe it's right I
don't remember that's that's where that
order came from is that we we chose the
bra to be a minus I and the C to be and
I think that's right with all of the
conventions I've used up till now okay
so it looks like that's the way it is
it's just the way it
is
H change the change it to minus
yeah yeah yeah yeah there's nothing uh
there's nothing sacred about the sign of
I I suppose that's the way it is I'm a
little surprised but
nevertheless oh no I think it's right I
I think it's right I think it's right I
think that's the right convention
although it's weird yeah I think all the
conventions are right yeah it's okay
it's
right all right so let's uh consider
then the connection between Pome
brackets and commutators there must be
some connection between them they must
somehow be the same thing or almost the
same
thing so let's look at various Pome
brackets and various uh and various
commutators and just see to what extent
they're similar to each other to what
extent they're different in fact we're
not going to bother with the differences
they are sometimes different but almost
in most contexts they're very similar to
each other plus brackets and commutators
so let's start with some function of
position it could be the position itself
and take its Pome bracket with
momentum the definition of that is DF by
DX DP by DP but that's just one H let's
write it DP by
DP minus d f by
DP DP by
DX this second term is zero on at least
to counts the F sorry the
the DF by DP first of all the F by DP is
zero p f doesn't depend on P and second
of all DP by DX doesn't P doesn't depend
on X so the second term here is
completely
zero the derivative of p with respect to
itself is one and we find the lovely
fact that the Pome bracket of any
function of x with p is just the
derivative of the derivative of f with
respect to X in other words the
operation of there should be a verb for
this a single verb for it but the
operation of Pome bracketing with
p
pling pling
with pling f with
p gives you DF by DX okay okay what
about commuting F ofx let's take F ofx
now to be a Quantum
operator what does it mean it means f
ofx is an operator which multiplies a
wave function by f ofx it takes any
function of x s of
X and multiplies it by F ofx to give a
new wave function that's the operation
Quantum mechanically of f ofx X let's
figure out what the commutator is of f
ofx with p to do that we just write down
F
ofx now p is minus I bar I'm going to
keep the the the har bars in for a
minute minus I should have kept the H
bars in here
also uh the H bar here is here okay if
you put a minus I there that that's
what's in this book as a infest
you think there's a minus sign I'm not
even going to try saying have K it's
minus huh it's correct as written or you
can have minus I and K oh I see I see
yeah okay
good right okay
so and I put the H bar back in because I
want to keep track of it there's no har
bar of course in classical physics
classical physics has no h bars all
right so let's take the commutator of f
ofx with Min - i d by DX that's what p
is and there's an H bar in there right
minus i h Bar D by
DX I want the commutata of f ofx with
this object over here that means I take
F ofx times this minus the opposite
order let's put a bracket around there
minus Min - I
HR d by
DX * F
ofx that's the commutator between F ofx
and the thing inside the bracket which
happens to be P now what do I do with
this how am I going to find out what
this is equal to the way to find out
what it's equal to is to apply it to an
arbitrary wave function any wave
function so let's take this and apply it
to an arbitrary wave function s of X and
see what we
get that's the way to figure out what a
diff What an operator does is apply it
to a wave
function okay let's see if we can figure
it out do I have the yeah okay first of
all the first term the first term gives
us f
ofx it gives us minus I minus I
bar that's from here f ofx and then the
derivative of s with respect to
X right d by DX Just Hits s of X and
differentiates it so what it does is it
multiplies it first differentiates and
then multiplies by F
ofx the second term gives me a plus I
plus I
hus * minus is plus h bar but now the
derivative operation
hits the product f ofx * s first F ofx
multiplies s and then you differentiate
you get two terms so let's put some
great big bracket around this we get two
terms the first term just differentiate
s leaving F alone so that gives you f
ofx time DC by
DX that's the first term the second term
differentiates F and leav S alone so
that gives me plus DF by
DX Time s of
X everything inside the bracket okay
that's the operation of this
commutator acting on a wave function s
now some terms cancel here's d s by DX *
I * - i h f here's the same thing with a
plus sign these can each other so we
might as well just erasee
them I think we've done this kind of
manipulation before but let's uh let's
do it this term cancels this
term all we have left is I
bar DF by DX now d f byx the F by thex
is just a function of X it's just a
function of X which we then multip mly
by S of
X here's what we learned we learned that
taking this complicated commutator and
applying it to any s of X is the same
thing as multiplying s of X by i d DF by
DX we can now write very simply that the
commutator is just
equal the commutator as an operator is
just equal to multiplication by i h bar
DF by DX so now I have a simple
formula the commutator of f with p let's
call it P
now minus P *
F has exactly the same op uh same
action as
multiplying by I DF by
DX well let's just compare that plusone
bracket pling with respect paing with P
gives us d f by DX commuting with P
gives us I H bar DF by
DX we could also do a similar
calculation to find out what the
commutator of X with a function of p
is this this is easy for one reason
remember there's this reciprocal
relationship between p and X they come
in completely parallel to each
other p and X can be sort of
interchanged they're simply Foria
transforms of each other and it wouldn't
be surprising if this formula just gave
way to a similar formula in which we
differentiate F in which we
differentiate F of p with respect to P
here when we commute f ofx with p we get
d f by DX here what you get is I bar the
F of
p with respect to
P so paing with either X or P
differentiates paing with P
differentiates with respect to x paing
with X differentiates with respect to P
now let me just see if if I have the
sign right I think I do yeah uh there's
an easy way to tell the easy way to tell
is supposing f ofx was nothing but X
itself let's write down what this says
if f ofx is just X then it says that the
commutator of X with
p is equal to I
bar time DX by DX that's just one so it
says commutator of X with p is IH bar
that's what happens if you just say f is
equal to X then DF by DX is 1 Let's
suppose that F of p is just
P then this would also say exactly the
same thing it would say commutator of X
with p is I bar * 1 so I have the sign
right if I had put another sign here I
would have an inconsistency between
these two
formulas commutator of X with p is I bar
what what's the plusone bracket of X
with
P that's
one we can kind of read off
this the relationship between Pome
brackets and
commutators they appear to be at least
in simple
situations they appear to be essentially
the same thing except for a factor of
I we can write this in the form that
Pome
bracket is equal to
commutator now where does the IH bar go
that's the
question uh I bar goes here I believe is
that
correct notice incidentally that the
commutator whatever it happens to be
let's say x and P as an example X and p
x and P
the commutator is much much smaller than
the Pome bracket by a factor of plunks
constant plun constant is a terribly
small number commutators are very small
that's natural because in classical
physics XP minus PX that's
zero commutators are zero in the
classical limit the limit that H bar is
equal to zero commutators are zero
they're only nonzero when H bar was not
equal to zero then so here we see how
har bar gets into the commutation
relations okay so let's just check a few
facts about commutators and uh and Pome
brackets and see that they're pretty
parallel to each other here's an example
a B plus
bracket what's the relationship between
that and I'm writing equal but I'm going
to change it in a moment
ba what's the relation well one of them
is derivative of a with respect to X
derivative of B with respect to P minus
the opposite the other one is exactly
the same thing except in the opposite
order they're negatives of each
other Pome brackets have this
anti-symmetry that Pome bracket of a
with B is minus the Pome bracket of B
with a well of course that's also true
of commutation
the commutator is AB minus
ba that's obviously
minus ba a minus
a here we have AB with a plus sign here
we have AB with a plus sign okay so Pome
brackets and commutators share the
property of anti symmetry it's called
that when you invert the order of the
two things which you're either paing or
commuting the sign changes so that's a
good sign they have some algebraic
similarity let me give you another
example which is a very useful fact when
you're trying to either compute quickly
commutators or Pome
brackets oh good an empty
Blackboard supposing you have a product
ab and you want to take its Pome bracket
with a third thing C you can build up a
lot of stuff by starting with some
simple things and constructing products
all right let's work out what that is
that's D
AB by
DX but let me work all right that's da
DX d c by
DP minus D
AB by DP d c by
DX but now let's work out the derivative
of
ab that's
a Time the X derivative of
B
plus b * the X derivative of
a all times the derivative of C with
respect to
p and this one is
minus a
the
[Music]
PB plus b d PA a all time d c by
DX now let's group these let's find all
the terms with a standing out in front
of them we have
a times something D
xB
DPC right d this is derivative of B with
respect to X derivative of C with
respect to P let's write it in the same
notation take this one and this one what
does it give
you it gives you a time the Pome bracket
of B with C look at it
a Time
dxb
DPC minus a * dpb
dxc that is nothing but a * the Pome
bracket of B with C now there's the
other term we've gotten rid of this and
we've gotten rid of this now there's the
term with B
undifferentiated two of them two terms
with B
undifferentiated so let's put the let's
put the B out
here and what does it multiply it
multiplies the X derivative of a * the P
derivative of C minus the opposite order
and that's just the Pome bracket of a
with
C it doesn't matter that I put the B on
the right here and the A on the left
we're talking about classical physics
classical physics the order of
multiplication doesn't matter I just
wrote it that way uh because that's the
way it comes out in quantum mechanics
but look what it says it says if you
have a POS with C it gives you a * B
with C plus b * a with C it's a simple
rule a simple rule that will carry you a
long ways in calculating plus
brackets let's compare it with
commutators let's do the corresponding
thing let's let's ask could it be the
same for
commutators
all right so let's take
AB commuted with C same operation except
in terms of uh
commutators this would
suggest that it's given
by
a commutator BC plus commutator AC with
B is this true or is it not true well
it's easy to find out on the left side
we have a b c minus c
a Ab is a is a single entity AB * C
minus C * a b do I have it right yes
that's the commutator let's check over
here here we have a * b c minus
CB that's the commutator of BC and here
we
have
AC minus CA
time
B let's see what we have we have ABC
here we have
ABC minus cab here we have cab with a
minus sign and then we have
ACB
minus ACB I
hope did I lose a minus sign oh oh yes
minus ACB plus ACB is zero so in fact
commutators have exactly the same
property as Pome brackets this tells you
if you only know some very simple Pome
brackets like just x with P you can
start building up complicated products
of x's and
PS and and commuting them or ping them
and you'll get the same answers you'll
get the same answers so Pome brackets
are the natural analog
sorry
uh commutators are the natural analog
aome
brackets uh the equality is not always
absolutely true and the reason is
sometimes you get expressions in quantum
mechanics which are a little which In
classical mechanics which are a little
bit ambiguous in quantum mechanics if I
do some complicated calculation and at
the end of the day I get uh X cubed
P then I don't know whether in in
quantum mechanics this stands for X
cubed P it might stand for X2
PX it might stand for X it might stand
for xpx S or it might stand for um for
xq uh PX cubed they're different
operators in quantum mechanics so there
is some amb uity that when you calculate
a Pome bracket you don't always know
exactly what it stands for in quantum
mechanics but apart from ambiguities
like this Pome brackets and commutators
are equal to within a factor of IH bar
all right so that's something that's
very useful and we'll use
it we're getting late so we're running
out of
time but I do want to
first I want to I'm going to do this
quickly now we're going to write the
schinger equation for a particle and a
potential and then we're going to study
the classical limit using these
principles to find out how the averages
of the wave packets move that's our goal
for tonight work out or to write down
the Schrodinger
equation for a particle moving in a
potential
we're not going to do much with it we're
not going to solve it we're just going
to calculate how a wave packet moves in
time all right the starting point is as
always I DCI by
DT x and
t is equal to H * s of x and t but now H
is not just going to be p² 2
m but it's going to be p^2 2 M plus some
potential energy
function which only depends on
X U of X is the potential energy it
corresponds to a force which is minus
the derivative of U with respect to X
and so we're going to plug that into
here what does the p^2 over 2 m give us
I've left out H bar incidentally and I'm
going to keep leaving out H bar for the
moment uh for the rest of the night left
out H bar what did we get before we got
p^2 over 2 m gave us I
believe - 1 2 m * second derivative with
respect to
X sorry I'm going to put back the H bars
but uh let's uh let's leave them out for
the moment that's the p^2 over 2 m term
what does U of x mean U of X just means
multiplication by the function U of X
that's all it means so the second term
here is plus u ofx * s of
x i d s by
DT this is the Schrodinger equation that
Schrodinger actually wrote down it says
the time rate of change of s is just
exactly what it was before plus an extra
term which is U of x * s of
X why is the S of X here why not just U
of X because U of X is an operator that
operates on the state Vector so always
there's a state Vector in there
somewhere either differentiated or
undifferentiated it's there this is the
shrodinger equation let's put in the H
bars again there an i h bar here I think
there's an H bar squar here and no har
bar at all
here okay that's Shing that is literally
the schinger equation that Schrodinger
wrote
down
yeah p is p aun t p is not a function of
T it's just it's just a different it's
it's an operation the average of p is a
function of
time the average of p is a function of
time and that's what we're going to
calculate P itself is just the operat p
i d by
DX it has no explicit time dependence
the fact that momentum changes with time
is the fact that its average changes
with time why does its average change
with time because side changes with time
not because P changes with time so
that's what I wanted this is the this is
the Schrodinger equation but I'm
actually more interested in the form of
the hamiltonian here's the form of the
hamiltonian and I want to compute I
would like to
compute how the average of X and P
change with time they change with time
because side changes with time this is a
complicated equation now a wave packet
may come in it may hit the potential
there's a potential U of X which let's
draw the potential as a dotted line
might look like this the wave packet
comes in experiences the fact that
there's a
potential previously it didn't have any
potential it did whatever it did which
may have been complicated but now it's
even more complicated it does something
because the potential is there and we
would like to find out on the average
what does it do on the average how does
the center of this wave packet
move right now the answer is that if the
wave if the potential is a very smooth
function if it varies very smoothly on
the scale of the oscillations of the
wave function then the center of the
wave function moves exactly according to
classical physics but let's see if we
can see
that uh we have the the rules for Pome
brackets and uh
commutators I'll erase off the
Blackboard here but of course we all
have them
memorized and we have here's the
equation here's the operative equation
that we want to apply that we want to
apply let's first figure out what should
we do let's first figure out how X how
the average of X changes with
time the average of X changes with time
this is DX
DT we don't have to stick in the wave
functions now and do the whole thing we
know it's just equal to the expectation
value of the
commutator of of well it's I bar I over
H
bar commutator of H which is p² over 2 M
plus U of X that's H with K and K is
just
X
okay first thing the commutator of U of
X with X is
zero a thing commutes with any function
of
itself x and x s commute x and x Cub
commute x with s of X commute because
all they are is multiplication by
functions of X and it doesn't matter
which order you you multiply them so the
first thing is in
calculating the commutator of the
hamiltonian with X U doesn't come into
it at all let's erase it U commutes
completely with X it's gone the
important thing is the commutator of X
with p^2 2
m let's write it down it's i
h 2 m in the denominator and then the
commutator of p^2 with X how do we
calculate the commutator of p^2 with X
we use this trick remember the trick
commutator
AB with C is a commutator
BC plus b c
a that's the trick we're going to use so
what's the commutator of p^2 with X just
this piece of it here is p commutate p
with
X Plus A and B are both P now A and B
are both P so it's p commutated PX plus
commutate PX with
P that's just using for a p^ 2 well
what's the commutator of p with
X not quite minus
I minus I bar commutator of X with p is
I commutator of p with X is minus I bar
each one of these commutators here is
just minus I bar minus I bar H bar was
just a number and all of this is just
equal to twice
- 2 I
bar time
P okay let's group it
together um on your formula above yeah
second part BC a May that should be AC
yeah I think so well a b with C is a
yeah yeah yeah yeah sorry a with C * B
good
okay all right let's group it together
and see what we have here we have I over
2 MH Bar and then we have Min - 2 I
let's just erase this and put - 2 I
HR
p i * I is
-1 that cancels this minus over here the
two cancels the two over here and the H
bars
cancel H bar cancels H bar two cancels
two I * I is min-1 and that cancels the
minus here and what's the net result the
result is p/
M average of p over M what have I
discovered I've discovered that the
average
velocity what is the what is this this
is just the average velocity of the
particle
is equal to the average momentum divided
by the
mass
okay not surpr well is it
surprising uh
not perhaps it's not so surprising
because if it wouldn't have come out
this way we would have said something's
wrong with the connection between
classical mechanics and quantum
mechanics but it does come out correct
that the average velocity is the average
momentum divided by the mass just as we
would expect now what about the average
what about the time the time dependence
of the momentum it's the time dependence
of the momentum which is given by fals
Ma force is time derivative of momentum
that's classical physics that's that's
the interesting part here let's see if
we can recover Newton's equations at
least as an average at least as an
average that's what we want to do is
recover Newton's equations Newton's
equation FAL Ma so let's apply exactly
the same rule to the Comm to
the average of momentum d by DP d by DT
and that's given by by by I over H
bar commutator
of p 2 P2 2 M plus u plus U of X with
what
P okay this time it's the U of X which
is
important p commutes with p^
s that's not there it's just the
commutator of p with U of X so this
whole thing is I over H
Bar
times the commutator of U of x
with
P do you remember what the commutator of
U of X with p is passing with P does
what it differentiates with respect to
x paing with P differentiates with
respect to X that was one of the first
things we worked out which has long gone
off the Blackboard
unfortunately but commuting with P also
differentiates with respect to
X well we worked that out that we worked
that out differentia uh sorry commuting
a function of X with P gives you the
derivative of the function of X and so
this all gives us then I over
H and then I can't remember then I think
it's plus plus another
I times uh H bar time DX
right H bar cancels har bar I * I is
minus and what we find out is that the
derivative of the
momentum is minus the derivative of U
with respect to X there's another word
for the D the derivative of U with
respect to X and it is force yeah it's
also the
gradient Force
F all right so first of all we find that
the velocity is given by p/ n M that's
one of the two equations of Newton
actually the definition of momentum and
the other piece of it is that the force
is equal to the time derivative of the
momentum that's all the content of
Newton equations force is derivative of
momentum it's actually mass time
acceleration since momentum we've
already
shown is M * velocity this says momentum
is M * velocity
and this says force is M * the
derivative of the Velocity which is the
acceleration so we see that
um the identification of minus i d by DX
with momentum and I D by DT with
hamiltonian as energy is a i i you can't
call it a correct identification what
you can say is that it's an
identification which in a classical
limit reprodu produces classical physics
that's the point the quantum mechanics
is more fundamental and you derive the
classical physics as an approximation
for
averages okay any questions and when you
did the U the U last semester and you
did the pant brackets you start you had
a way where you actually set down a set
of postulates you just use the
definition and I get two of them where
where you reverse the uh the ABC Rule
and then there was also one where you
reverse in the show is negative there
some others if you do those are those
all
analogous no would you say that in
classical mechanics what you have is a
is a resultant Force whereas in quantum
mechanics you don't get a resultant
Force because you have the whole thing
evolves the
average is is is a rough equivalent of a
resultant Force what's a resultant for
result do adding with adding vectors
well when you take the the gradient of a
function obviously it has vectors
pointing in in other direction well here
we're only doing one
dimension at the
[Music]
moment the preceding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at stanford.edu